我们已经涵盖了很多主题。我们已经谈到了视觉的演变。我们
We have covered a lot of topics. We have talked about how the sense of vision evolved. We
谈到了人类视觉的细节。我们看了一些动物的种类
have talked about the details of human vision. We have looked at some of the variety of animal
视力。我们已经讨论过视觉是一个眼睛积极引导的过程
vision. We have talked about how vision is a process where the eye is actively steered
在场景周围，以最大限度地了解特定场景。
around the scene in order to maximise our understanding of that particular scene.
因此，现在讨论机器人和视觉，并了解机器人如何使用是恰当的
So now it is appropriate to talk about robots and vision, and look at how robots have used
为了能够以与人类相似的方式执行任务的视觉感
the sense of vision in order to be able to perform tasks, in a similar way to which humans
和动物使用视觉来执行任务。左边的机器人是一个非常有名的机器人
and animals use vision to perform tasks. The robot on the left is a very famous robot
叫沙基。20世纪60年代在SRIInternational开发。它有一台电视摄像机
called Shakey. Developed at SRI International in the 1960s. And it has a television camera
在顶部，它用于导航。右边的机器人就是我建造的机器人
on the top, which it uses for navigation. The robot on the right is one that I built
在21世纪初，它已经拥有相当多的摄像头，他们是一个
in the early 2000s, and it has got quite a number of cameras on board, and they are a
看看有点有趣。在前面是一个立体相机对，它是一个
little bit interesting to look at. In the front is a stereo camera pair and it is a
有点像我们自己的两只眼睛。它允许机器人确定三维结构
bit like our own two eyes. It allows the robot to determine three dimensional structure of
在它面前的世界。在顶部，它有一个非常闪亮的镜像对象，这是一部分
the world in front of it. On the top, it has a very shiny mirror object and that is part
我们称之为全景相机组件。有一个摄像头抬头看着那面镜子
of what we call a panoramic camera assembly. There is a camera looking up at that mirror
并且允许机器人看到360度-它可以看到前进，后退和侧向。
and that allows the robot to see 360 degrees—it can see forwards, backwards and side ways.
它有时被称为全向摄像机或全景摄像机。
It’s sometimes called an omni-cam or a panoramic camera.
这个机器人的最后一个摄像头是侧面的广角摄像头。它有一个鱼眼镜头，
The last camera on this robot is a wide-angle camera on the side. It has a fish eye lens,
所以它几乎有一个半球形的视野。这可以看看发生了什么
so it almost has a hemispherical field of view. And that can look at what is happening
到机器人的一侧。目前的火星探测器，好奇号探测器，
to the side of the robot. The current Mars Rover, the Curiosity Rover,
它拥有大量的摄像头，用于各种功能。
has got a large number of cameras on board that it uses for a variety of functions.
现在看教学机器的业务是计算机视觉领域，那
Now the business of teaching machines to see is the field of computer vision, and that
是一项自20世纪60年代以来一直在进行的活动。一些重要的早期工作
is an activity that has been going on since perhaps the 1960s. Some important early work
由麻省理工学院的拉里·罗伯茨（LarryRoberts）作为博士项目的一部分进行。拉里接着说
was carried out by Larry Roberts at MIT as part of his PhD project. Larry went on to
做其他非常重要的事情，并在创建互联网方面发挥了重要作用。所以
do other very important things and was very instrumental in creating the internet. So
在他的论文作品中，他正在做的是拍摄一个物体的照片，这是非常的
in his thesis work what he was doing was taking a picture of an object, and this is a very
简单的木块对象，用电视摄像机拍照，并试图锻炼
simple wooden block object, took a picture with a TV camera and was trying to work out
它的形状是什么。所以他经历了许多视觉处理步骤，这些都是
what shape it was. So he went through a number of vision processing steps and these are the
我们将在以下讲座中介绍的各种事情。
sorts of things we will cover in following lectures.
最初的步骤之一是找到这个物体的边缘，一旦找到了边缘
One of the first steps was to find the edges of this object and once he had found the edges
他会尝试将线段与这些边缘相匹配，一旦他知道这些线条
of the object he would try to fit line segments to those edges and once he knew those line
他知道图像的形成方式。然后他可以说些什么
segments, he knew something about the way images are formed. He could then say something
关于这个特定物体的三维形状。所以我们在这里有
about the three dimensional shape of this particular object. So what we have here is
一个可以拍摄图像并对其进行处理并提出三维模型的系统
a system that can take an image and process it and come up with a three dimensional model
那种形状。所以它是一种非常简单的物体识别形式。电脑需要
of that shape. So it is a very simple form of object recognition. The computers take
一个图像，并讨论它正在看什么样的对象。那是
an image and made a discussion about what sort of object that it was looking at. That’s
足够的信息，然后机器人进行移动，去挑选该对象和
sufficient information then for a robot to make a move, go and pick that object up and
或许以某种方式操纵它。那么为什么视觉是机器人的良好传感器呢？
perhaps manipulate it in some way. So why is vision a good sensor for a robot
具有？我认为视力是重要且非常实用的原因有几个
to have? There are a few reasons why I believe vision is an important and very practical
用于机器人的传感器。首先，相机本身现在非常
sensor for a robot. Firstly, the cameras themselves are now very
价格便宜，其原因在于摄像机内置于一切;内置于细胞中
cheap and the reason for this is because cameras are built into everything; built into cell
手机，内置于笔记本电脑等。所以实际传感器相当于视网膜
phones, built into laptops, and so on. So the actual sensor the equivalent of a retina
现在是一种可能花费不到1美元的设备。镜头较小，镜头较小
is now a device that perhaps costs less then a dollar. Lenses are smaller, cameras are
小而便宜。另一个非常重要的原因
small and cheap. The other reason that is really important
是计算现在真的很便宜;我们有非常强大的计算机芯片和很多
is that computation is now really cheap; we have very powerful computer chips and lots
和大量的内存，所以这使我们能够运行算法来处理数据
and lots of memory, and so this enables us to run algorithms to process the data that
来自传感器芯片。所以这种组合非常有效，高
comes out of the sensor chip. So this combination of very effective, high
分辨率，颜色，便宜的传感器，丰富的计算是我们的基础
resolution, colour, cheap sensors, with abundant computation are the foundations on which we
可以建立机器人视觉系统。这是Ray的一张非常有趣的图表
can build robot vision systems. Here is a really interesting graph from Ray
Kurzweil，他谈了很多关于计算能力随时间变化的方式，以及
Kurzweil, and he talks a lot about the way computation power has changed over time, and
这是一个对数垂直标度，他正在绘制一些代表的数据点
this is a logarithmic vertical scale and he’s plotting a number of data points that represent
随着时间的推移，你每秒可以购买一千美元的计算量。和
a number of calculations per second you can buy for a thousand dollars over time. And
我们可以看到这是一个对数垂直尺度的指数图。它是什么呢
we can see that this is an exponential plot on a logarithmic vertical scale. So what it
显示的是计算确实在增加，随着时间的推移越来越快。这是
is showing is computation is really increasing, increasingly rapidly with time. And this is
从根本上说，RayKurzweil的论文。所以，如果我们将此推断到未来，
fundamentally Ray Kurzweil's thesis. So if we extrapolate this into the future,
我们可以看到我们在这里，我们有一个有效的计算能力
we can see that we are about here, and we have computational power of effectively one
小鼠脑。到20世纪20年代初，我们应该拥有一千个
mouse brain. By the early 2020s we should have, for a thousand
美元，人类大脑的计算能力。到2050年，当你们许多人将会
dollars, the computational power of a human brain. And by 2050 when many of you will be
活着，也许是在你工作生涯的最后，你会花一千美元
alive, perhaps at the ends of your working careers, for a thousand dollars you will be
能够购买相当于地球上所有人类大脑的足够计算能力。
able to buy enough computing power to the equivalent of all human brains on the planet.
这是一个非常惊人的预测，非常非常非常激动人心的时刻。
That is a pretty amazing prediction and so clearly very, very exciting times ahead.
那么机器人专家对传感器视觉做了哪些实际的事情呢？
So what practical things have roboticists been doing with sensor vision?
我们最近听到很多关于自动驾驶汽车，谷歌汽车等等，但实际情况
We hear a lot in recent times about self-driving cars, Google cars and so on, but the actual
自动驾驶汽车的历史可以追溯到很久以前。有一些非常重要的研究
history of self-driving cars goes back a long way. There was some very significant research
20世纪80年代欧洲的计划叫做普罗米修斯，并且做了很多非常基础的工作
program in Europe in the 1980s called Prometheus, and a lot of very fundamental work was done
一位叫ErnstDickmanns的科学家。他自动化这辆面包车。它有很多相机
by a scientist called Ernst Dickmanns. He automated this van. It had a number of cameras
在前面向外看，它能够高速驾驶高速公路。
in the front looking outwards, and it was able to drive along autobahns at high speed.
这辆特定的货车和一些货车取得了许多重要的里程碑式的成就
A number of significant landmark achievements were made by this particular van and some
它的直系后代。另一项具有里程碑意义的成
of it immediate descendants. Another landmark achievement was from some
来自卡内基梅隆大学的研究人员，他们主要使用传感器自动化汽车
researchers from Carnegie Mellon University, who automated a car primarily using the sensor
愿景，并将其驱逐到美国各地。旅程花了几天，大约四千公里，
vision, and drove it across America. The journey took a few days, around four thousand kilometres,
并且人为干预的人数相对较少。这个视频显示了一个人形机器人接球。
and there were relatively few human interventions. This video shows a humanoid robot catching a ball.
在这里，我们再次以慢动作看到它。
Here we see it again in slow motion.
现在机器人头部有一对摄像头，
Now the robot has a pair of cameras in its head,
这允许它估计到球的距离;使用该信息进行建模
which allows it to estimate the distance to the ball; uses that information to model
球如何在空间中移动以规划手臂应该采取的动作
how a ball moves through space in order to plan the motion that the arm should take to
拦截球。因此，机器人的头部有许多传感器：一对相机
intercept the ball. So the robot’s head has a number of sensors: pair of cameras as
我提到过，但也有一些倾斜传感器，所以它可以解决头部指向的位置
I mentioned, but also some tilt sensors, so it can work out where the head is pointing
在太空。现在你可以看到左眼和右眼看到的球的位置
in space. Now you can see the positions of the ball as seen by its left and right eye
作为时间的函数，在这里你可以看到机器人手移动的动画
as a function of time, and here you can see an animation of the robot’s hand moving
拦截球的路径。这是我们实际看的飞行机器人
to intercept the path of the ball. Here is a flying robot which we actually looked
在机器人技术课程中，你们中的一些人在关闭机器人视频中近距离观看
at up close in the Out and About with Robots video, in the Robotics course some of you
可能早些时候见过。这个机器人再次配备了立体声相机。再说一遍
might have seen earlier. This robot is equipped with a stereo pair of cameras again. So again
就像我们自己的两只眼睛一样，这使机器人能够通过工作来感知它前面的障碍物
like our own two eyes, this enables the robot to sense an obstacle in front of it, by working
使用两个信息从前面的世界的三维结构
out the three dimensional structure of the world in front using information from two
相机和船上的大量处理。
cameras and a fair amount of processing on board.
我自己和CSIRO的一些同事以及这个水下机器人开发的另一个机器人
Another robot developed by myself and some colleagues at CSIRO, and this underwater robot
还有一对立体声相机。它有两个向下看的摄像头
has also got a stereo pair of cameras. It has got two cameras that look downwards and
两个向前看的相机。向下看的摄像机正在估算距离
two cameras which look frontwards. The downward looking cameras are estimating the distance
来自机器人的海底，这个机器人正试图保持恒定的高度
of the seabed from the robot, and this robot is trying to maintain a constant altitude
在海床上面。它使用来自的三维信息来做到这一点
above the sea bed. And it does that using the three dimensional information from the
向下看的立体相机。前视立体摄像机用于探测障碍物。
downward looking stereo cameras. The frontward looking stereo cameras are used to detect obstacles.
在这里，我们看到了世界的样子
Here we see what the world looks like through
移动机器人的眼睛。这个特殊的机器人有一个允许的立体相机对
the eyes of a mobile robot. This particular robot has got a stereo camera pair which allows
它创造了一个通过它移动的世界的三维模型。和
it to create a three dimensional model of the world through which it is moving. And
这对于确定它可以驱动的平面是非常有用的
that is really useful in order to determine what is a flat surface that it could drive
过去，什么是墙，或人，或其他一些障碍。
over, and what is a wall, or human being, or some other kind of obstacle.
在这里，我们有一些不同的东西。在这里，我们有一个向下看的相机
Here we have something a bit different. Here we have a single camera looking downwards
在珊瑚礁，摄像机由机器人携带。现在我们可以使用一个数字
at a coral reef, and the camera is being carried by a robot. Now we are able to use a number
数学技术结合来自这些多个摄像机视频的信息
of mathematical techniques to combine the information from these multiple camera videos
创建珊瑚礁的三维模型。我们从一些单曲做到这一点
to create a three dimensional model of the coral reef. We do this from a number of single
相机视图。现在我们平滑那个三维网格;我们将原始图像覆盖在上面
camera views. Now we smooth that three dimensional mesh; we drape the original imagery over it
创建纹理贴图表面。所以现在我们有一个非常逼真的三维视觉
to create a texture map surface. So now we have a very realistic looking three dimensional
从一系列单一摄像机视图中获得的珊瑚礁模型。
model of a coral reef obtained just from a whole sequence of single camera views.
所以我希望我已经说服你，愿景是一个真正非常重要的传感器
So I hope that I have convinced you that vision is a really, really important sensor for all
各种各样的动物，为自己和机器人。所以在本课程的其余部分我们是
sorts of animals, for ourselves and also for robots. So in the rest of the course we are
要了解我们如何做机器人视觉;我们如何从相机中获取信息
going to learn something about how we do robot vision; how do we take information from camera
传感器并处理它并生成机器人可以采取某些行动的信息。
sensors and process it and generate information that a robot can take some action on.